today we're going to talk about
something that is gaining traction and
is looking more and more like a viable
way of improving your health at least
here in modern times it's been around
for centuries maybe even millennia and
that's the use of water hot water or hot
steam
whether you call it hydrotherapy or
sauna and what is the science behind how
this type of therapy can help you not
only in the acute setting but if done on
a regular basis could also help your
longevity so this is something that
they're looking into with great detail
so we have known as human beings for a
long time that there are health benefits
associated with bathing in baths so this
this goes back for millennia
the romans used to do it in fact there
is a city in great britain called bath
and it's because of the baths that were
there it actually was a ancient roman
city
that's not where this is but you can see
here that these people here are also
bathing so what's the science behind it
there's a lot of different ways today
that you can use
water
steam heat
to help your
longevity we can use showers
you can use tubs you can use saunas as
we see here in the upper right hand
corner and also apply hot packs to the
body is this you know all kind of like
loosey-goosey science or is there
actually something behind it and what
you'll see here as we talk about
we'll talk about this as hydrotherapy
but it can also be used in terms of
something called contrast showers baths
saunas or even fermentations and
generally speaking what you'll see used
over and over again and this goes back
in terms of tradition for many many
years now the science is burying this
through is that there is a long period
of heat
where
the subject or the patient is exposed to
heat and they sweat
and then right at the end of it they're
exposed to a short period of cold and
that is something that we see with
contrast showers that is something that
we see with baths that is something that
we see in sauna use this is uh in
finland where
saunas are used extensively for a long
period of time in this regard
but okay not just finland in many many
countries of the world especially in
europe uh but we look at finland because
so many people in finland do sauna so
it's an interesting country to research
they do the same thing they they go into
the sauna for a long period of time and
then they come outside and actually hit
themselves with a little branches of the
tree or they might roll around in the
snow and then sometimes they'll even
repeat this again so this is not
uncommon to repeat this cycle but it's
always the same cycle of heat at the
beginning and a short amount of cold at
the end
so let's talk about saunas first because
i think a lot of people are familiar
with that asana basically they have
different types there's infrared saunas
which we won't talk about here and are
ways of trying to duplicate what we see
in saunas so there's very various ways
of heating up some saunas that are
infrared versus simple heat sometimes
they're moist sometimes they're dry
and sometimes that makes it difficult to
do studies because there's different
varying ways
i think the temperature that you want to
think about if you're talking about a
regular sauna
is to getting up to 174 degrees
fahrenheit and sustaining for at least
20 minutes
followed by a cooldown you can repeat
that about two to three times that's
generally how saunas are used we'll talk
about how
what the science is behind this
in finland it's very common about 99 of
the people in finland actually do saunas
and or do sauna as they would call it
most do it at least once a week others
of them will do it at you know every day
so that's seven times per week
so what happens of course is when you go
into a hot room or when you apply hot
packs this can be applied to you know
showers or even fermentations as the
skin temperature raises first and then
finally the core body temperature and
you can actually get core body
temperatures
up to 102 degrees fahrenheit or 39
degrees
celsius
in doing just this and what that will do
is it will
increase the cardiac output so the
amount of energy that the heart is using
and the heart is expending so it's
almost like exercise
and there will be actually an increase
in the volume of your plasma that's the
blood volume and also there'll be an
increase in sweating we'll talk more
about sweating in terms of getting rid
of toxins
and things that can be gotten rid of in
sweat that not necessarily can be gotten
as rid of as easily in
your urine or in your stool
one of the things that's very
interesting about heating up the core
body temperature is this thing in terms
of heat shock protein so heat shock
proteins are enzymes that the body has
that the body uses
to help fold proteins in the appropriate
manner and when things get hot
those proteins in your body that are
working normally can become
unfolded and that's a that's a problem
with too much heat that's why your body
wants to regulate your body temperature
well these heat shock proteins go out
and they re-fold the proteins back
and so it's important to have heat shock
proteins if you're going to be exposed
to heat and so what we notice is this
people who are exposed to heat over and
over and over again will have an
improvement or an increase in the
function of their heat shock proteins
which makes them more able to deal with
heat
but that's not all that heat shock
proteins are involved with they're also
involved with immune function which of
course is very important cell signaling
and regulation of protein folding like
we talked about before
saunas also increase interferon we'll
talk more about that in a little bit so
cytokine release this is all a part of
your immune system and immune functions
and something called mitochondrial
biogenesis this is a nice way of just
saying basically mitochondria which are
the powerhouses of your cells these are
like the engines that run your cells
they can duplicate themselves more when
you are in saunas where there's repeated
heating and cooling sessions that you
have on a weekly basis
getting more technical there's some
other things that can increase like nrf2
this regulates the heat shock proteins
and it also is involved with
regulation of inflammation both of
pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory
proteins and it's involved in
cardiovascular disease so you can see
here that just heating your body up and
cooling it down has more
effects than just temperature it
actually
affects your immune system it affects
your inflammatory system it affects your
cardiovascular system and folks here's
the point increases in fox o3 proteins
and sirtuins now if you don't know what
those are these are proteins that are
been recently on the stage and really
hot topics for those that are dealing
with or looking at longevity why do
people live longer well the proteins
that they're seeing that are
involved in living longer are also
improved and increased when you go into
saunas and when you take hot showers and
things of that nature when you increase
the body temperature and then cool down
so it's going to be important to learn
about this because i think this has a
real importance in terms of those who
are interested in living longer and
healthier
il-6
which is an interleukin this is involved
in inflammatory things comes from
exercise it increases inflammation it
also stimulates il10 which reduces
inflammation so inflammation is not all
bad right so if you've got an infection
you want inflammation to attract the
attention from your immune system to
deal with that invader but then you
don't want inflammation from the rest of
your life right you want to actually be
able to cool that down and so there are
cell signaling pathways that reduce that
and get rid of inflammation after you're
done dealing with the issue
so it's complex it's not something that
you can just say black and white this is
good this is bad
but what
regulates all of this is your immune
system your body and if we can improve
your body by improving
heat and cold then that is something
that's worthwhile looking into so this
is kind of little a little bit of a
foray into what we're talking about
today and how this might work
okay so
let's talk a little bit about
cardiovascular health
and
these research studies are coming out of
finland at just breakneck speed and the
reason is is because
everybody in finland does sauna and so
it's really easy to study but people do
it in different amounts some people do
it seven times a week like we talked
about most people just do it maybe zero
to one times per week and as we said
ninety-nine percent of the people in
finland uh do so in fact it's it's kind
of interesting if everybody in finland
wanted to at the same time go into asana
there would actually be enough room
in the saunas in the country of finland
to accommodate everybody that's how
popular it is people do this literally
on a nightly basis
so here's a study that was published in
complementary therapies in medicine just
a couple of years ago
where they took 19 healthy volunteers 12
male 7 female mean age was about 46
years of age
and they did 25 minutes
in a sauna session with an exercise load
of about 60 to 100 watts which is a
moderate amount of exercise
and so what did they find
they found that when they did this
they actually found that blood pressure
drops
when you get into the sauna so that's
important to understand
or at least that's what they thought
they would find what they actually found
was that contrary to previous reports
that blood pressure drops during the
sauna stay what they found was that
actually blood pressure went up
during
a sauna session not only blood pressure
but also heart rate meaning what they're
saying here is that sauna use is almost
equivalent to exercise
this is really important because i can't
tell you how many people i've seen in my
clinic
that say doc i'd love to exercise but my
knee
or my foot
or my this or my that or my other and
i'm saying to you is that well if if
your heart is able to tolerate this kind
of exercise it may be beneficial for you
to think about investing in a sauna or
getting hot cold therapy on a regular
basis in some other way either through a
spa
or
you could even as we'll talk about later
warm up towels
and in a microwave and apply it to you
in a safe way we'll talk a little bit
more about that but what we're saying
here is that if you can't get the
exercise that you need
or even if you can get the exercise that
you need a a way of enhancing that
exercise may be sauna use because what
we're seeing here is physiologically
some things that are identical acute
heat exposure they found in the sauna is
a burden comparable to moderate
physical
exercise
and the sustained decrease in blood
pressure after heat exposure
suggests that the sauna bath will have a
beneficial effect on the cardiovascular
system so in other words you're in the
sauna blood pressure goes up you're done
there's a sustained reduction in blood
pressure afterwards and this may
actually be very beneficial
in terms of circulation getting the
blood to circulate around in your body
to clean out the toxins
to uh to to give nutrients to your cells
and also to improve your cardiovascular
health so interesting study
published just recently but wait
there's more information because
some people might say well those that
are using the sauna may be noticing
better health benefits because people in
general who are more health conscious
may be using the sauna but actually as
it turns out when you look at this
association between the amount of sauna
so the people that use it only one time
per week versus those that use it two to
three times per week uses though versus
those that use it four to seven times
per week and you can see here that
there's a significant reduction in
relative risk for
fatal cardiovascular and all-cause
mortality events i mean this is huge
folks
okay this is this is all cause mortality
events notice that the more you use
sauna there's a dose respondent curve
that there is a reduction in relative
risk for all cause mortality and you can
see here this is not a small study this
is
2300 patients looking at sudden cardiac
death
fatal coronary heart disease fatal
cardiovascular disease and all-cause
mortality
and there is so much data here i mean in
terms of congestive heart failure
sauna use showed a benefit in reduction
in
pvcs which are arrhythmias
improved endurance heart size and
ejection fraction that's really key when
you're talking about congestive heart
failure and there's the the source what
about ischemic heart disease this is
coronary artery disease this is what is
so prevalent here in western diets and
cultures what do they see with sauna use
improved vascular endothelial function
and folks you don't even have to
exercise you just need to do the sauna
so hot cold hot cold peripheral artery
disease improvements in pain endurance
and blood flow if you've got
claudication we call it or pain in your
calves because maybe in the past you've
smoked or you've had ischemic heart
disease things of that nature sauna
bathing may actually be beneficial so
sauna use
and or
contrast showers etc what about
elevated lipids
total reduction total cholesterol by
five points that's actually
impressive there and reduced ldl by two
to three points
not not in like a year in just two weeks
there was a reduction and of course
inflammation reduction in crp increase
in il-10 which we said before was
beneficial at reducing inflammation so
definitely some benefits here to your
cardiovascular system with
sauna use
but you know unlike medications that we
give sometimes that are good for one
particular thing but have side effects
in another category
sonobathing actually is beneficial all
around here
so as you can see here in terms of
alzheimer's disease there was an
increase in brain derived neurotrophic
factor this is one of the things that it
actually improves
the cleanup of the proteins that are not
necessary in your brain these proteins
have been shown to lead to alzheimer's
disease and there was an actual um
relative risk reduction
four times per week versus just one time
per week there was a
a reduction
down to 0.35 that's a that's a 65
reduction
that's amazing
and that's the the source for that what
about depression
it improved the antidepressant effect
what about growth hormone this is what's
so
beneficial for people young who are
growing but also for people who are
older and want to feel like they're
young growth hormone
has been researched extensively for this
type of effect and there was
improvements in pain endurance and blood
flow
and then far infrared saunas reduces
fasting glucose levels in people who are
diabetic so again documented these are
these are major journals and it showed
that there was a benefit
what about those who are really
interested in physical fitness so those
of you who are doing exercise because
you're in competitive sports
this is a real boon here i mean
endurance 30 minutes two times a week
increased endurance
in just physical exercise so those who
are in the cross country team
they want to get
better for their 5k run in terms of
getting better times highly recommend
looking into sauna use how about
preventing muscle loss so as you get
older one of the problems is that you
actually lose muscle mass and daily heat
treatments even locally prevented muscle
atrophy
okay so what about toxins so
there are certain heavy metals that you
may be exposed to especially if you're
living in inner cities where the pipes
may be old there may be lead things of
that nature well guess what
those heavy metals the body needs to get
rid of it's actually 17 times easier for
your body to get rid of a lot of those
heavy metals in sweat than it is in the
urine so sweating out these toxins may
actually be beneficial in terms of the
way your body gets rid of things and
what better way to sweat of course than
in a sauna
if you are drinking lots of fluid that's
going to be very important
so some of the things that can be
excreted in sweat
is bpa remember for a long time bpa is
was used and they finally got rid of bpa
and guess what they went to
bpb
and there's bpc and there's all these
forever chemicals in these compounds
that are being used in plastics and
non-stick things
by polychlorinated phenols
phthalate compounds used in shampoos all
of these things accumulate they can
actually be excreted in sweat so getting
rid of these things may be beneficial in
terms of detoxification so highly
recommend that you look into
heat therapy and we'll talk more about
how to do that you know not everybody
can afford to buy a sauna or to buy a
spa those are not cheap right so there
are ways that you can do this for really
inexpensive and still get the benefit
and we'll talk more about that
but you know speaking of sauna that's
not for everybody right so you need to
make sure that you're drinking lots of
water because you can lose a lot of
water when you sweat in these saunas and
if you're pregnant
there's could be health risks associated
with the fetus if you heat up the
temperature too much so be aware of that
but i will just tell you that in finland
there's a lot of women who are pregnant
that do it anyway
i just be careful and maybe delay that
until you have delivery of your baby
children two plus it's okay but remember
that their body
volume to surface ratio is such that
they can lose and gain lots of heat real
quickly so you you've got to be careful
with small children in these saunas okay
let's talk about hydrotherapy now so
we're moving away from saunas and we're
talking about the use of
moist heat on the body this is something
that
the world has been doing for many
centuries probably even millennia even
outside of saunas so let's talk about
the science about this and what's going
on
and specifically in the acute setting so
in the acute settings we're talking
about is when you actually have an
infection
and you under have to understand the
cells of the immune system so we've got
a nice little graph here about what it
is that's going on
so the first thing you need to
understand is that there are two
arms of the immune system there is the
innate immune system which is able to
recognize invaders
not based on specific proteins but just
in general and molecular patterns and
then there's the adaptive immune system
this is part of the immune system that
makes t cells b cells antibodies
based on what your body has seen before
so this adaptive immune system needs to
be educated
and the innate immune system does not
need any education whatsoever it can
tell right off the bat if something is
foreign or if something is self and so
for instance if you were to get an
infection or a vaccine the adaptive
immune system would make antibodies and
rev those up against that specific
invader but if that invader mutated in
some way the adaptive immune system
might be a little bit back on its heels
whereas the innate immune system would
be just fine now as it turns out with
some of these viruses that we've seen
for instance let's talk about covid or
sarskovi too
there are actual proteins in sarskovi
too that shut down the innate immune
system so that it can escape and
actually multiply and that's when the
adaptive immune system tries to capture
it and gets gets it away the key that
you should understand here is that the
innate immune system
gets weaker with age
so you might notice that in children
they don't really get serious as often
uh coven 19 infections but they do make
a lot of good fever they make a lot of
good heat and that heats up the body and
this is what we've been talking about in
this session so understand that the
innate immune system is the first
barrier it doesn't depend on specific
proteins it can recognize what is
foreign and it gets weaker with age no
matter how good your immune system is it
gets weaker with age so anything that
you can do to improve
your innate immune system is going to be
very very beneficial
okay
so one of the major products of the
innate immune system is something called
interferon and it's well named because
this substance this protein that is
produced by lymphocytes
actually interferes
with viral
infections let's read here what nancy go
wrote
way back at the beginning of the sars
cov2 pandemic she wrote studies of sars
and mers suggests that the interferon
response is delayed
compared with coronaviruses that cause
mild disease with milder cases of those
two coronaviruses that can cause severe
disease the patients with severe sars or
mers had higher
viral loads and delayed
interferon responses
thus
it could be that the patients with most
susceptible to severe disease are those
that cannot mount an effective early
antiviral immune response
a study of 50 patients with cases
ranging from mild to severe found that
gene expression profiles indicating type
1 and type 2 interferon responses were
highest
in patients with mild to moderate
disease and were low
in patients with severe or critical
disease
a similar difference in type 1
interferon activity was detected in the
serum from the patients patients with
more severe disease had less
type 1 interferon activity in their
blood so you should understand then that
interferon is very important from the
very beginning when the patient gets
infected if you want to have a mild
infection and actually here's the
graphic data that goes along with this
you can see here on the y-axis we have
interferon alpha-2 concentration and
interferon activity on this one and you
can see here very clearly that people
that have mild disease
had higher concentrations of interferon
people with mild disease had higher
interferent activity compared to those
that had more severe or critical disease
here was another study this one was
published in the prestigious journal
science that showed that people that had
mutations in their interferon
factors here
so very low interferon all of these had
severe disease
those that had antibodies against
interferon just because they had an
autoimmune condition where unfortunately
their body's antibodies neutralized
their own interferon all of these had
very severe disease
and their antibodies were low
those that had no antibodies notice they
have very good responses and most of
these had
no severe disease in fact what they said
here in the karolinska institute they
said together these two papers explain
nearly 14 of all severe coven 19 cases
that's pretty amazing actually and i
agree with that statement
so let's get down to the biochemistry of
what's actually going on
for that we go back to a study that was
done 20 years ago where they actually
looked at
heat
and the influence of hypothermia on
monocytes
which as we said are part of the innate
immune system and can
recognize the elimination of these
pathogens regardless of whether they
mutate or not okay so this is really
important this is a way of of getting
around that adaptive immune system and
boosting the innate immune system so in
this case 12 healthy volunteers were
immersed in a bath
at 39.5 degrees celsius
and they measured
all of these different factors that
we're talking about and they exposed
them to
a endotoxin receptor and the complement
receptors after the hot
water bath and what they found was this
three hours after this hypothermia the
response of monocytes
to the endotoxin was enhanced
because of the fact that they were at a
higher temperature
and so they concluded that the thermal
effect of fever
directly activates monocytes which
increases their ability to respond to in
this case bacterial challenge but let me
also say that these very same monocytes
are also the ones that respond in viral
and
parasitic infections all sorts of
infections and so
a body when it produces a fever is
actually part of the immune system
it's part of the
response
that your system is doing against the
invader and so it's really important
that you don't try to suppress that
fever unless it's of course really
really high in causing seizures or
or very high heart rates
so we talked about the heat part what
about the cold part afterwards well this
was a study that was
published in the journal
physiology
and was conducted at the university of
toronto
by a grant from the us military and what
they did was they exposed these guys to
cold after heat
and notice what happened here when we're
looking at natural killer cells there
was an increase
in the amount of natural killer cells
and also an increase in the amount of
linux units here at 35 degrees celsius
and then finally at 38 you can see that
there was an increase
then exercise and then exercise at 35
degrees
celsius so these are the different
different types of categories and here
they did duration of cold exposure at
zero
60 and 120 minutes so there was an
actual increase here uh in in all of
these categories and they say here that
this study suggests that despite popular
beliefs that cold exposure can
precipitate a viral infection the innate
component of the immune system is not
adversely affected by a brief
period of cold exposure indeed the
opposite seems to be the case the fallen
core body temperature resulting from
cold exposure led to a consistent and
statistically significant mobilization
of circulating cells an increase in
natural killer selectivity and
elevations in circulating il-6
concentrations
and to meet the statistical significance
notice folks they only needed seven
people in the study to reach statistical
significance that means that this is a
very
powerful effect
let's go back to heat and covet 19
specifically here here's a paper that
was published looking at the amount of
interferon gamma
that was secreted from
people after different core body
temperatures and notice what they found
in the study that if you increase core
body temperature at 37 to 37.5 to 38 the
38.5 finally boom right there at 39
that the amount of interferon gamma that
was secreted from lymphocytes after
stimulation was almost 10 fold higher
that was an incredible amount of
interferon that you're getting this
happens to be the very same
molecule
that is beneficial at preventing viral
infections like coven 19 and so it could
be said that at least if we connect the
dots here
it would be interesting to see what a
randomized controlled trial of
hydrotherapy would do in patients who
are just coming on with sars kovi to
infections or indeed any kind of viral
infection where they start to feel like
they're having body aches and things of
that nature
so it's an interesting thing because
not only are we thinking about this now
but people have thought about this in
the past as well and here's a paper i
want to just sort of show you to prove
the point this was published over a
hundred years ago
and over 100 years ago we had something
here in the united states and and
actually around the world called the
spanish flu pandemic
or the influenza pandemic
calling it the spanish flu is kind of a
misnomer i don't believe it actually
came from spain
but uh it was called that for many years
and so that's what people know it as but
this is dr wells ruble now dr wells
ruble was a physician he was also the
medical director of a sanitarium in the
northeast of the united states
specifically the the new england
sanitarium and these sanitariums were
founded on the principles that
natural remedies
could actually be beneficial in treating
people so people would go to these
sanitariums to get rest to feel better
to get sunshine fresh air and and they
were escaping the growing uh hustle and
bustle of the cities of the day and so
dr wells rubel was well versed in the
ideas of hydrothermal therapy or
hydrotherapy that were pioneered by dr
jackson in upstate new york and also by
dr john harvey kellogg who is the
medical director at the world's largest
hospital at the time the battle creek
sanitarium and so when this spanish flu
pandemic
came around this is what dr wells ruble
wrote
in a journal periodical called life and
health on may 1st
in 1919 titled as we see it he said the
present epidemic of influenza has
furnished an excellent opportunity to
test out the efficacy of rational
treatment
in dealing with respiratory disorders
especially in conditions accompanying
and following attacks of influenza so
what did he mean by rational treatment
he was talking about rest he was talking
about exercise he was talking about good
nutrition he was talking about sunlight
exposure and also
very specifically
hydrotherapy so let's see what he
proposed to do in his article so at the
time there were army hospitals who had
the latest and the best in terms of
technology they
they had the ability they had something
that just come out at this time was
aspirin aspirin was was uh invented in
1899 by the german company bayer
and it was actually extracted from bark
and it was a very powerful
antipyretic which means that it was able
to stop
fever it was an anti-inflammatory and at
the time when people got influenza there
was a lot of inflammation that was
associated with the body's
dealing with the influenza and so the
feeling was is that if we could get rid
of the symptoms of influenza you might
be able to make some improvements so
these people were getting very high
fevers
muscle aches body aches and aspirin was
doing a very good job of getting rid of
it and if it didn't work when maybe you
had to give a higher and even higher
dose
so
that's what was being used in the army
hospitals and of course they had the
best physicians and the best resources
to boot
so if you understand influenza you
should understand one thing and that is
is that
typically there is the feeling of the
body aches that we all have gotten when
we've gotten influenza in the past but
with the spanish flu it led in a number
of cases to getting pneumonia
and of course this was in 1919 this was
well before antibiotics had been
discovered penicillin being discovered
in 1928
and so you can see here is that
generally speaking in the army hospitals
and we don't know exactly the number but
they did publish this and dr ruble was
able to get the numbers here about 20
percent of the camp um were those that
came down
about 16 percent of those people
who came down with influenza developed
pneumonia
and you can think about most if not all
of these were getting aspirin which of
course kills the fever and of course
gets rid of inflammation and then of
those getting pneumonia
40 percent of those
ended up dead which gives you an
infection fatality ratio of 6.4 percent
which is fairly high i mean if you
consider
the uh the standards and of course it
could have been much higher than that we
don't really have great records from
that time we don't know exactly how many
people got infected in the world we do
know a little bit about how many people
died but generally speaking 16
got pneumonia 40 died of those that got
pneumonia now compare that to 10 of the
sanitariums in the northeast where dr
ruble pooled the
data
on those that were treated as inpatients
so these were people that they could
observe the the treatments that they
were giving the fermentations as they
called it
they were going out into the sun they
were getting fresh air they were eating
appropriate diets that were not rich in
inflammatory factors and you can see
here that in those that came down there
was about 446 in the sanitariums
being treated in the sanitariums that
came down with influenza and
they did not use aspirin they did not
use these things but rather hydrotherapy
which heightened fever which heightened
the inflammatory response especially
that of the innate immune system and
shut down the virus early on and whereas
16 percent developed pneumonia in the
army camps only 2 percent of those in
the sanitariums went on to develop
pneumonia
and
that was only 11. now you can imagine
that
that you know without x-rays without
antibiotics and these were your
run-of-the-mill physicians here in the
sanitariums not necessarily the bright
uh youth of the of the uh
the army hospitals instead of 40 percent
dying of pneumonia there was about 55
percent of those that died of pneumonia
of course there was small numbers to to
begin with about six died
leaving us with an infection fatality
ratio of only 1.1 percent
and you can see here that
they would made the
argument
that the treatment modalities that they
were using in the sanitariums were
better superior and rational compared to
what was being done in the army
hospitals of course this was not a
peer-reviewed published journal but an a
observation
from dr wells rubel one of the medical
directors
of um of this
new england sanitarium by the way he
later became the president
of a organization on the west coast
called the college of medical evangelist
which was established at loma linda
california now
the ancestor of loma linda university so
interesting
notes
so where did he get this information
from well this is not
gotten out of a vacuum this was actually
being looked at this wasn't something
secret or special
a
psychiatrist by the name of julius
wagner ureg
who was living in austria at the time
also noticed that people who developed
fevers seemed to get better from their
other
problems that they had and uh
one of the things that he noticed in his
insane asylums dr yorick wagner
was that he noticed that people who had
neurosyphilis and again remember this is
before penicillin people who had
neurosyphilis and started developing
psychiatric issues seemed to get better
after they had a fever for some
particular other reason
so what he decided to do was uh
something very um
interesting at the time and it was uh
kind of raised some eyebrows but he
decided since they had the treatment for
malaria down pretty well with
uh a quinine was he would take people
with malaria take their blood and inject
their blood into those people who had
neurosyphilis
and of course the expected problem there
of course would be that they would
develop malaria in addition to their
neurosyphilis
the bonus being that they would develop
these very high fevers and what would
the high fevers do of course is it would
prime the innate immune system to do its
job find these invaders the trempanims
the syphilis eradicate them and then
when that was done the patient would
then be cured of their malaria
with the known treatment which was the
quinine and
notice what it says here in this article
that was published in 2013 about this
fever therapy in the treatment of
neurosyphilis he said in the following
years of his discovery artificial fever
was induced by any one of the following
methods the introduction into the
patient of a parasitic disease the
injection of a foreign protein
injections of chemical substances such
as sulfur electrical means such as the
administration of diathermy or
radiotherapy or placing the patient in
an electromagnetic field and simple
immersion of the individual in a hot
bath or placing them in a heat cabinet
dr wagner's therapy was highly admired
and was used on neurosyphilis cases well
into the 1950s
and as you may recall penicillin was
discovered in 1928 however with the
induction with the introduction of
penicillin in syphilis treatment fever
therapy effectively
ended now why did it end it's because
giving
a penicillin tablet
is far easier
and much less labor-intensive
than doing heat therapy as you'll see
when we learn a little bit more about
heat therapy it can be labor intensive
and that can be very very expensive
especially as you cannot
scale
human capital right you need many many
people to do many many fermentations but
if you are able to scale
the production of medication to a large
degree you're able to actually do that
much better
unfortunately the problem is is that
while we've just discovered that heat
therapy has many other side benefits
as we know today medications have side
effects like penicillin allergy
and
wiping out good bacteria as opposed to
just the bacteria that you want to wipe
out so
there are good things obviously i will
use antibiotics in my icu when i have to
when my back is against the wall and a
patient is about to die
i don't care about good bacteria when a
patient is about to die i care about
killing the bad bacteria and so
different situations call for different
remedies but if this is what you're
trying to do and you want to do it in a
way that has the least amount of side
effects sometimes doing this can
actually be
beneficial as well so
realize that there was a time and a
place
in society when heat therapy was
actually well recognized and used not by
people who were considered alternative
but by the main thinkers of our society
so
here's the question in the last slide
and uh
sort of what i want to talk about is
what should you do what what can you
learn from this presentation that you
can apply in your life
where the rubber hits the road
take advantage every day most people
take showers every day or at least every
other day
take an advantage here and shower hot
for about five minutes
and then at the very end cold for one
minute you can repeat it a couple of
times if necessary but i've talked to
people who have done this and i do this
myself
and
i don't drink coffee but for those who
do drink coffee the amount of energy
they say they derive from doing this
practice is like that of a cup of coffee
in the morning especially if you're
doing it in the morning
some people do it at night and it's
interesting i find that if it's done in
the morning along with your circadian
rhythm it tends to give you energy and
if you do it at night it tends to calm
you down a little bit
so i think it's it's actually quite
beneficial so that's the first thing
that you can do
if you have access to a hot tub
heat it up to about 104 degrees
fahrenheit which is about the maximum
that you can actually do in the united
states because they kind of set that as
a as a goal you can't really go much
higher than that
do it for about 20 minutes and then
follow it up with a cold plunge okay so
these are sorts of things as we call um
tonics or prophylaxis this is stuff that
you should do on a daily basis to keep
your body
in
in flux so that there is a buildup of
those heat shock proteins as a
preventative
now if you were to come down with a
viral infection
then you may need to do something more
than that but i would even say even for
these things like contrast showers or
hot tubs make sure
that your physician is okay with doing
this there are a couple of conditions
where you may not want to do this for
instance if you have a heart condition
that causes your heart to go fast uh you
don't want to be passing out in the
shower or in a hot tub those are kind of
dangerous places so just make sure that
they okay it for you
and
and follow up okay so what about if you
actually get sick
so for that you want to get a little bit
more extreme and that is something we
call a fermentation i just refer you to
a couple of reference websites
if you will one of them is called
hydrotherapy at home dot com that's all
one word and the other one is hydro the
number four
covid dot com
and those have excellent resources that
take you through step by step about how
to do a fermentation i'll just kind of
briefly describe it for you here
basically what you're going to do is you
want to place these hot towels
on your body to heat it up for about 20
minutes and then remove them
and submit yourself to something cold
for about a minute and the way we do
that is
getting your
so laying down on on either the carpet
or something that the the carpet is
protected because there's going to be
some water
and you've got your feet in a bath of
basically as hot as water as you can
tolerate without burning your skin now
i'll just say that for those of you who
are diabetic and can't feel your feet
you're going to probably want to skip
this because you don't want to burn your
feet that's going to cause some problems
so make sure that you don't do that
and you can you can heat up these towels
in various different ways you can boil
water on a stove and put the the towels
in there you can put towels that are
soaked in a microwave
sometimes they even have devices that
are like heating blankets that are you
know heat up more than a heating blanket
um and and you can use that to keep
things hot but basically what you're
going to do is you're going to put a hot
towel on the bottom you're going to lay
on this with a layer of towel in between
so you don't get directly burned by that
towel so it's kind of like a two towel
layer so that the towel that's touching
your skin is is dry and not heated and
then the heat is going to penetrate
through that towel by another towel on
the other side that's heated and wet
and you're going to do this both on your
back and on your front and you're going
to put your feet if you can in a hot
bath and then you're going to cover up
and so essentially what's going to
happen is that heat is going to get
transferred to your body you're not
going to be able to cool yourself down
and so your body is going to sweat
profusely and so you want to make sure
that you're drinking lots of water
before you do this and you do this for
about 20 minutes and usually someone is
helping because the towels will not
remain hot long enough so you got to
continuously be heating up towels and
putting them on there so that you do
this so the point is is that you're
heating up you're making an artificial
fever for yourself
now when you get done with the 20
minutes you pull all of this off you put
your feet in ice cold water and you get
a
an ice cold towel
and that's wet and you basically apply
it to the chest
and you kind of rub up and down to kind
of uh
it's called mitten friction and the
reason why this happens well there's a
lot of reasons and a lot of cultures
that have done this for hundreds of
years the the fins when they come out of
a sauna will take a stick and kind of
hit themselves with a stick
and
other people do it or they might take
leaves or they might you know just sort
of rub themselves and the purpose here
is to get the white blood cells
that are
stuck to the walls of your blood vessels
often into circulation to do what it is
that they need to do so there's always
something called demargination which is
where these white blood cells which are
stuck off to the side come into
circulation and do what they need to do
when you take a cold shower so if you
were to take a cold shower and measure
the number of white blood cells in
circulation those would definitely go up
and and that's what you're aiming to do
is to get those white cells into
circulation and traveling around your
body looking for the infection going to
the infection and actually taking care
of it so that's kind of a fermentation
and it's an alternative and it's
actually probably out of all the things
on here it's it's probably one of the
most effective things to do and it's
actually pretty cheap everyone has
access to hot water everyone has access
to towels you don't have to be
with money to buy
saunas what you're buying there is
convenience all of these things can be
done if you put the time in and do it
what you're supposed to do
i would definitely say one of the
biggest risks in doing hot fermentations
is burning yourself either the person
doing the fermentations or the person
helping you with it both of you can get
burned so you have to be very careful
and
and and be cognizant of the fact that
especially if people have difficulties
with skin sensation so if diabetics
can't feel their feet you got to be
careful that you're not gonna burn
okay so what about sauna so saunas we
talked about the very beginning here's
my recommendation based on the data you
really ought to be getting the sauna up
to 174 degrees fahrenheit for at least
20 minutes and doing it about three
times a week and then ending with colds
and then the major benefits that we
talked about from that were reviewed and
we've talked about that
okay so we've talked about hydrotherapy
we've talked about fermentations we've
talked about sauna we've talked about
the use of artificial fever in patients
and in subjects not only to treat
specific infections and specific acute
indications but also overall for
cardiovascular health
for neurological for mood
and for overall mortality so there's a
lot of benefits to this and it should be
used in conjunction i would recommend
highly that you talk to your physician
to make sure that there's not something
that you haven't thought about that may
be a harmful thing based on your
conditions and you here's the key drink
lots of water making sure you're you're
well hydrated because you can lose lots
of water when you're doing this type of
activity and make sure you don't burn
yourself so
very interesting data and i think things
that we can apply in our lives right now
in real life in real time to make a real
difference
so i want to thank you for joining us
for real health on tuesdays and uh this
is dr roger schweltz signing off thanks
for joining us